Rui Ramos

Address: Av. D. Manuel II, 1552 1ºE, 4470-334 Maia Email: <u>rui.ms.ramos@gmail.com</u> | Telephone: +351 916506589

PERSONAL STATEMENT

A committed, knowledgeable and capable BigData Engineer, highly experienced in Systems Administration, with significant expertise in HPC and BigData systems. Agile experienced profissional with strategic planning and management skills. A designer and architect of new services and IT platforms envolving Distributed Systems and Data. A confident presenter and teacher, able to impart complex information to audiences of all levels.

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

02/2016 - Present

Big Data Engineer | Farfetch

- Design and develop highly scalable, end to end process to consume, integrate and analyze large volume, complex data from sources such as Hive, Flume, Kafka or Storm
- Build fault-tolerant, adaptive and highly accurate data computational pipelines.
- Improve existing ETLs to Hive and Spark. Implement new processes on the DataLake platform and work closely with Data Scientists to transform Big Data into model ready forms to support analytic projects

03/2009 - 02/2016

Systems Administrator | University of Porto

 Working in the Administration and Computational Unit at the Rectory of the University of Porto. Managing Central Services for the University as DNS, Mail, Identity Management, eLearning platforms, HPC/Grid, Private Cloud, Web Hosting and Digital Repositories.

03/2006 - 03/2009

HPC & Grid Computing Specialist| University of Porto

 Development and Administration of a High Performance Computational service based on GRID technology as Tier-2 for <u>EGI</u>

07/2004 - 11/2004

Researcher | LIACC - Artificial Intelligence and Computer Science Laboratory

Integrated in MIMO "Models and Infra-structures for Mobile Computing" project at LIACC
"Laboratory of Artifitial Inteligence and Computer Science" where i was responsible for
developing a Java compiler for a distributed language.

02/2004 - 06/2004

Software Developer | Finantech

Development of a Market system application. A .NET C/C++ application using the FIX protocol. This work was made in the context of a final project for graduation in Computer Science. more info (http://www.finantech.pt/marketsystem.aspx)

EDUCATION

1999 - 2004

Universidade do Porto

BSc: Computer Science

PUBLICATIONS

• Studying the feasibility of (quasi)real-time spatio-temporal applications using grid infrastructures

Jun 2012 publication descriptionConference: Joint GISELA-CHAIN Conference

 UPORTOaai - The Authentication and Authorization Infrastructure at the University of Porto

Conference: EUNIS 2011 Maintaining a sustainable Future for IT in Higher Education, At Dublin, Ireland

International Summer School on Grid Computing 2007

ICEAGE - Sweden

Certifications

- Functional Programming Principles in Scala
- Relational Database Support for Data Warehouses
- Data Warehouse Concepts, Design, and Data Integration
- Database Management Essentials
- CS105x: Introduction to Apache Spark
- edX Verified Certificate for Big Data Analysis with Apache Spark

Supporter

- GreenPeace
- Wikimedia Foundation

REFERENCES ON REQUEST

https://www.linkedin.com/in/ruimsramos/